<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Open_science on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/open_science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Open_science on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/open_science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Papers publizieren. Versuch einer Anleitung</title>
      <link>/2018/01/25/papers-publizieren-versuch-einer-anleitung/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/25/papers-publizieren-versuch-einer-anleitung/</guid>
      <description>Unter https://sebastiansauer.github.io/Talks-ses/#/ finden sich die HTML-Folien zu einem Talk von mir zum Thema, wie man Papers publiziert (oder es zumindest versucht).
Der Quelltext findet sich in diesem Github-Repo.
Der Talk steht unter der CC-BY-Lizenz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I am unavailable for review</title>
      <link>/2017/01/17/unavailable_for_review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/17/unavailable_for_review/</guid>
      <description>Dear editorial team,
Thanks for considering me for review. After some thought-meandering I came to the conclusion that traditional publishers - such as the present publisher of this journal - support a business model that I deem unfair and inappropriate for regular science and for the interests of science and scientists alike. That is, the fees are much too high thereby sucking resources out of the science system and out of society which could be used for the better otherwise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to promote open science? Some practical recommendations</title>
      <link>/2016/09/22/openscience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/09/22/openscience/</guid>
      <description>I just attended the biannual conference of the German society of psychology (DPGs) in Leipzig; open science was a central, albeit not undisputed topic; a lot of interesting related twitter discussion.
image source: Felix Schönbrodt
Interestingly, a strong voice of German scientiests uttered their concerns about being scooped if/when sharing their data (during the official meeting of the society). This being said (sad), the German research foundation (DFG) has updated its guidelines now stressing (more strongly) that publicly funded projects should share their data, with the rationale that the data do not belong to the individual scientiest but to the public, as the public funded it (I find that convincing).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>