<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>association on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/association/</link>
    <description>Recent content in association on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/association/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Covariance as correlation</title>
      <link>/2017/04/25/cor_as_cov/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/25/cor_as_cov/</guid>
      <description>Correlation is one of the most widely used and a well-known measure of the assocation (linear association, that is) of two variables.
Perhaps less well-known is that the correlation is in principle analoguous to the covariation.
To see this, consider the a formula of the covariance of two empirical datasets, $X$ and $Y$:
$$COV(X,Y) = \frac{1}{n} \cdot \big( \sum (X_i -\bar{X}) \cdot (Y_i - \bar{Y}) \big) $$
In other words, the covariance of $X$ and $Y$ $COV(X,Y)$ is the average of difference of some value to its mean.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some reflections on stochastic independence</title>
      <link>/2016/11/08/stochastic_independence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/08/stochastic_independence/</guid>
      <description>We are often interested in the question whether two variables are &amp;ldquo;associated&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;correlated&amp;rdquo; (I mean the normal English term) or &amp;ldquo;dependent&amp;rdquo;. What exactly, or rather in normal words, does that mean? Let&#39;s look at some easy case.
NOTE: The example has been updated to reflect a more tangible and sensible scenario (find the old one in the previous commit at Github).
Titanic data For example, let&#39;s look at survival rates of the Titanic disaster, to see whether the probability of survival (event A) depends on the whether you embarked for 1st class (event B).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why absolute correlation value (r) cannot exceed 1. An intuition.</title>
      <link>/2016/08/28/why-abs-correlation-is-max-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/08/28/why-abs-correlation-is-max-1/</guid>
      <description>Pearson&#39;s correlation is a well-known and widely used instrument to gauge the degree of linear association of two variables (see this post for an intuition on correlation).
There a many formulas for correlation, but a short and easy one is this one:
$$r = \varnothing(z_x z_y)$$.
In words, $$r$$ can be seen as the average product of z-scores.
In &amp;ldquo;raw values&amp;rdquo;, r is given by
$$ r = \frac{\frac{1}{n}\sum{\Delta X \Delta Y}}{\sqrt{\frac{1}{n}\sum{\Delta X^2}} \sqrt{\frac{1}{n}\sum{\Delta Y^2}}} $$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intuition on correlation</title>
      <link>/2016/07/25/correlation-intuition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/07/25/correlation-intuition/</guid>
      <description>reading time: 10 min.
Pearson’s correlation (short: correlation) is one of statistics’ all time classics. With an age of about a century, it is some kind of grand dad of analytic tools – but an oldie who is still very busy!
Formula, interpretation and application of correlation is well known.
In some non-technical lay terms, correlation captures the (linear) degree of co-variation of two linear variables. For example: if tall people have large feet (and small people small feet), on average, we say that height and foot size are correlated.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>