<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>causality on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/causality/</link>
    <description>Recent content in causality on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/causality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>On a mediator-type causal analysis</title>
      <link>/2020/07/17/on-a-mediator-type-cuasal-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/17/on-a-mediator-type-cuasal-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Load packages library(tidyverse) library(ggdag) library(GGally)  A DAG Consider this DAG:
dag1 &amp;lt;- dagitty::dagitty(&amp;quot;dag{ x -&amp;gt; y -&amp;gt; z }&amp;quot;) dag1 #&amp;gt; [1] &amp;quot;dag {\nx\ny\nz\nx -&amp;gt; y\ny -&amp;gt; z\n}\n&amp;quot; #&amp;gt; attr(,&amp;quot;class&amp;quot;) #&amp;gt; [1] &amp;quot;dagitty&amp;quot; ggdag(dag1) + theme_dag_blank() Let’s asume that’s some causal pathway of the next study you happen to tap into.
Would it be sensible to run this regression:
`y ~ x + z
Let’s simulate that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Causal language appears to be wide-spread in psychological journals, even if not warranted</title>
      <link>/2020/07/01/causal-language-appears-to-be-wide-spread-in-psychological-journals-even-if-not-warranted/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/01/causal-language-appears-to-be-wide-spread-in-psychological-journals-even-if-not-warranted/</guid>
      <description>Load packages library(tidyverse)  Science is concerned about causality, to a large degree Science does not learn much from correlations (association). If you disagree, explain what we learn from the fact that, say, storks and babies are associated (as the saying goes).
I think that readers will not doubt that we do not learn much from this association. Why? Because we know that the correlation is not “real”, it is spurious.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Correlation is intransitive -- a simulation</title>
      <link>/2020/06/11/correlation-is-intransitive-simulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/11/correlation-is-intransitive-simulation/</guid>
      <description>Load packages library(tidyverse) library(MASS) library(rockchalk)  Correlation is not transitive It has probably been known since a long time that correlation is not transitive. However, in practice the error of assuming that correlation would be transitive is some times committed.
For example, Nassim Taleb has pointed out that (some or all) psychologists would commit such an error when they state “genes are correlated with IQ, IQ is correlated with performance, hence genes are correlated with performance”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When adding variable hurts – The collider bias</title>
      <link>/2020/06/04/when-adding-variable-hurts-the-collider-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/04/when-adding-variable-hurts-the-collider-bias/</guid>
      <description>Load packages library(tidyverse) library(conflicted) library(ggdag) library(broom) library(GGally)  Motivation Assume there is some scientist with some theory. Her theory holds that X and Z are causes of Y. dag1 shows her DAG (ie., her theory depicted as a causal diagram). Our scientist is concerned with the causal effect of X on Y, where X is a treatment variable (exposure) and Y is the dependent variable under scrutiny (outcome).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulating Berkson&#39;s paradox</title>
      <link>/2020/04/16/simulation-berkson-s-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/04/16/simulation-berkson-s-paradox/</guid>
      <description>This post was inspired by this paper of Karsten Luebke and coauthors.
We’ll stratify our sample into two groups: students (Studium) and non-students (kein Studium).
Structural causal model First, we define the structure of our causal model.
set.seed(42) # reproducibilty N &amp;lt;- 1e03 IQ = rnorm(N) Fleiss = rnorm(N) Eignung = 1/2 * IQ + 1/2 * Fleiss + rnorm(N, 0, .1) That is, aptitude (Eignung) is a function of intelligence (IQ) and dilligence (Fleiss), where the input variables have the same impact on the outcome variable (aptitude).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
