<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Plotting on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/plotting/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Plotting on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/plotting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing around with dumbbell plots</title>
      <link>/2018/05/23/playing-around-with-dumbbell-plots/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/23/playing-around-with-dumbbell-plots/</guid>
      <description>Dumbbell plots can be used to show differences between two groups. Bob Rudis demonstrated a beautiful application of such plots using ggplot2 board methods.
In this plot, I will explain or comment his code, and adapt a few changes.
First, load some packages.
pacman::p_load(tidyverse, ggalt) Let’s make up some data. Tip: Make up some data conveniently in Excel, copy it to the clipboard, and then paste it as tribble (see below) into R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing around with dataviz: Comparing distributions between groups</title>
      <link>/2018/05/18/playing-around-dataviz-comparing-distributions-between-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/18/playing-around-dataviz-comparing-distributions-between-groups/</guid>
      <description>What’ a nice way to display distributional differences between a (larger) number of groups? Boxplots is one way to go. In addition, the raw data may be shown as dots, but should be demphasized. Third, a trend or big picture comparing the groups will make sense in some cases.
Ok, based on this reasoning, let’s do som visualizing. Let’s load some data (movies), and the usual culprits of packages.
library(tidyverse) library(mosaic) data(movies, package = &amp;quot;ggplot2movies&amp;quot;) Now let’s add a variable for decade as year is too fine grained.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing around with dataviz: Showing correlations</title>
      <link>/2018/05/18/playing-around-with-dataviz-showing-correlations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/18/playing-around-with-dataviz-showing-correlations/</guid>
      <description>In this plot, we are looking into some ways of displaying association between (two) quantitative variables, aka correlation. Our goal is to present a rich representation of the correlation.
Let’s take the dataset flights as an example.
data(flights, package = &amp;quot;nycflights13&amp;quot;) library(tidyverse) library(viridis) flights %&amp;gt;% filter(arr_delay &amp;lt; 100, dep_delay &amp;lt; 100) %&amp;gt;% ggplot(aes(x = dep_delay, y = arr_delay, color = origin)) + geom_point(alpha = .01) + geom_smooth(se = FALSE, color = &amp;quot;grey20&amp;quot;) + geom_rug() + facet_wrap(~origin) + scale_color_viridis_d() ## `geom_smooth()` using method = &amp;#39;gam&amp;#39; and formula &amp;#39;y ~ s(x, bs = &amp;quot;cs&amp;quot;)&amp;#39; Points are not the only geom that make sense here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Showcase of Viridis, maps, and ggcounty</title>
      <link>/2018/05/18/showcase-of-viridis-maps-and-ggounty/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/18/showcase-of-viridis-maps-and-ggounty/</guid>
      <description>This posts shows how easy it can be to build an visually pleasing plot. We will use hrbrmster’s ggcounty, which is an R package at this Github repo. Graphics engine is as mostly in my plots, Hadley Wickhams ggplot. All build on R. Standing on shoulders…
Disclaimer: This example heavily draws on hrbrmster example on this page. All credit is due to Rudy, and those on whose work he built up on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick intro to geo plotting</title>
      <link>/2018/05/17/quick-intro-to-geo-plotting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/17/quick-intro-to-geo-plotting/</guid>
      <description>Geo plotting can be simple; at least in its basic form. Let’s review an example using data from GADM.
GADM provides maps for many (all?) countries of the world; not only the country borders but even administrative border lines an a finder scale.
It comes very handy that the map (geo) can be downloaded as R data files:
data_path &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;https://biogeo.ucdavis.edu/data/gadm3.6/Rsf/gadm36_DEU_2_sf.rds&amp;quot; Load some packages:
library(sf) library(tidyverse) library(downloader) Download the maps data:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualisation of interaction for the logistic regression</title>
      <link>/2018/04/02/visualisation-of-interaction-for-logistic-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/02/visualisation-of-interaction-for-logistic-regression/</guid>
      <description>In this post we are plotting an interaction for a logistic regression. Interaction per se is a concept difficult to grasp; for a GLM it may be even more difficult especially for continuous variables’ interaction. Plotting helps to better or more easy grasp what a model tries to tell us.
First, load some packages.
library(tidyverse) ## ── Attaching packages ──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── tidyverse 1.2.1 ── ## ✔ ggplot2 2.2.1.9000 ✔ purrr 0.2.4 ## ✔ tibble 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intuition to Simpson&#39;s paradox</title>
      <link>/2018/03/09/intuition-to-simpson-s-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/09/intuition-to-simpson-s-paradox/</guid>
      <description>Say, you have to choose between two doctors (Anna and Berta). To decide which one is better, you check their success rates. Suppose that they deal with two conditions (Coolities and Dummities). So let’s compare their success rate for each of the two conditions (and the total success rate):
This is the proportion of healing (success) of the first doctor, Dr. Anna for each of the two conditions:
 Coolities: 7 out of 8 patients are healed from Coolities Dummieties: 1 out of 2 patients are healed from Dummities  This is the proportion of healing (success) of the first doctor, Dr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zusammenhang von Lernen und Noten im Statistikunterricht</title>
      <link>/2017/12/20/zusammenhang-von-lernen-und-noten-im-statistikunterricht/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/12/20/zusammenhang-von-lernen-und-noten-im-statistikunterricht/</guid>
      <description>Führt Lernen zu besseren Noten? Eigene Erfahrung und allgemeiner Konsens stimmen dem zu; zumindest schadet Lernen des Stoffes nicht und hilft oft, gute Noten bei einer Prüfung zu diesem Stoff zu erzielen. Aber welche Belege, wissenschaftliche Belege gibt es dazu? An unserer Hochschule, die FOM, haben wir eine kleine Untersuchung zu dieser Frage durchgeführt. Genauer gesagt haben wir unseren Studierenden einen Statistik-Test vorlegt und gefagt, wie sehr sie sich für diesen Test vorbereitet hätten.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A p-value picture</title>
      <link>/2017/11/29/a-p-value-picture/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/29/a-p-value-picture/</guid>
      <description>Much ado and to say about the p-value. Let me add one more point; actually not really from myself, but from Diez, Barr, and Cetinkaya-Rundel (2012), p. 189; good book in one is looking for “orthodox” statistics.
library(tidyverse) ## ── Attaching packages ──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── tidyverse 1.2.1 ── ## ✔ ggplot2 2.2.1.9000 ✔ purrr 0.2.4 ## ✔ tibble 1.4.2 ✔ dplyr 0.7.5 ## ✔ tidyr 0.8.1 ✔ stringr 1.3.1 ## ✔ readr 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive diagrams in lieu of shiny?</title>
      <link>/2017/11/27/interactive-diagrams-in-lieu-of-shiny/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/27/interactive-diagrams-in-lieu-of-shiny/</guid>
      <description>One frequent use of the Shiny server software is displaying interactive data diagrams. The pro of using Shiny is the great flexibility; much more than “just graphics” can be done. Basically Shiny provides a flexible GUI for your R program. But if you simply aiming at displaying or exploring some data interactively, a much simplor approach may do it for you; there are some nice libraries available in R for that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping foreigner ratio to AfD election results in the German Wahlkreise</title>
      <link>/2017/10/22/afd-map-foreigners/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/22/afd-map-foreigners/</guid>
      <description>In a previous post, we have shed some light on the idea that populism - as manifested in AfD election results - is associated with socioeconomic deprivation, be it subjective or objective. We found some supporting pattern in the data, although that hypothesis is far from being complete; ie., most of the variance remained unexplained.
In this post, we test the hypothesis that AfD election results are negatively associated with the proportion of foreign nationals in a Wahlkreis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping unemployment ratio to AfD election results in German Wahlkreise</title>
      <link>/2017/10/10/afd-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/10/afd-map/</guid>
      <description>There is the idea that the alt-right German party AfD is followed by those who are deprived of chances, thoses of fearing to falling down the social ladder, and so on. Let&amp;rsquo;s test this hypothesis. No, I am not thinking on hypothesis testing, p-values, and stuff. Rather, let&amp;rsquo;s color a map of German election districts (Wahlkreise) according to whether the area is poor AND the AfD gained a lot of votes (and vice versa: the area is rich AND the AfD gained relatively few votes).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping unemployment rate to German district areas</title>
      <link>/2017/10/09/unemp-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/09/unemp-map/</guid>
      <description>A chloropleth map is a geographic map where statistical information are mapped to certain areas. Let&amp;rsquo;s plot such a chloropleth map in this post.
Packages library(sf) library(stringr) library(tidyverse) library(readxl)  Geo data Best place to get German geo data is from the &amp;ldquo;Bundesamt für Kartografie und Geodäsie (BKG)&amp;rdquo;. One may basically use the data for a purposes unless it is against the law. I have downloaded the data 2017-10-09. More specifically, we are looking at the &amp;ldquo;Verwaltungsgebiete&amp;rdquo; (vg), that is, the administrative areas of the country, ie.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drawing a country map</title>
      <link>/2017/10/06/chloromap/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/06/chloromap/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s draw a map of Bavaria, a state of Germany, in this post.
Packages library(tidyverse) library(maptools) library(sf) library(RColorBrewer) library(ggmap) library(viridis) library(stringr)  Data Let&amp;rsquo;s get the data first. Basically, we need to data files:
 the shape file, ie., a geographic details of state borders and points of interest the semantic information to points of interest eg., town names  Shape file The shape file can be downloaded from this source: http://www.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Different ways to present summaries in ggplot2</title>
      <link>/2017/09/08/ggplot-summaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/08/ggplot-summaries/</guid>
      <description>A convenient and well applicable visualization for comparing groups with respect to a metric variable is the boxplot. However, often, comparing means is accompanied by t-tests, ANOVAs, and friends. Such tests test the mean, not the median, and hence the boxplot is presenting the tested statistic. It would be better to align test and diagram. How can that be achieved using ggplot2? This posts demonstrates some possibilities.
First, let&amp;rsquo;s plot a boxplot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Print csv-file tables as plots</title>
      <link>/2017/06/22/tab2plot/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/22/tab2plot/</guid>
      <description>tl;dr Use this convenience function to print a dataframe as a png-plot: tab2grob().
Source the function here: https://sebastiansauer.github.io/Rcode/tab2grob.R
Easiest way in R:
source(&amp;quot;https://sebastiansauer.github.io/Rcode/tab2grob.R&amp;quot;)  Printing csv-dataframes as ggplot plots Recently, I wanted to print dataframes not as normal tables, but as a png-plot. See:
Why? Well, basically as a convenience function for colleagues who are not into using Markdown &amp;amp; friends. As I am preparing some stats stuff (see my new open access course material here) using RMarkdown, I wanted to prepare the materials ready for using in Powerpoint.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sorting the x-axis in bargraphs using ggplot2</title>
      <link>/2017/06/05/ordering-bars/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/05/ordering-bars/</guid>
      <description>Some time ago, I posted about how to plot frequencies using ggplot2. One point that remained untouched was how to sort the order of the bars. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at that issue here.
First, let&amp;rsquo;s load some data.
data(tips, package = &amp;quot;reshape2&amp;quot;)  And the usual culprits.
library(tidyverse) library(scales) # for percentage scales  First, let&amp;rsquo;s plot a standard plot, with bars *un*sorted.
tips %&amp;gt;% count(day) %&amp;gt;% mutate(perc = n / nrow(tips)) -&amp;gt; tips2 ggplot(tips2, aes(x = day, y = perc)) + geom_bar(stat = &amp;quot;identity&amp;quot;)  Hang on, what could &amp;lsquo;unsorted&amp;rsquo; possibly mean?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple way of plotting normal/logistic/etc. curve</title>
      <link>/2017/05/24/plotting_s-curve/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/24/plotting_s-curve/</guid>
      <description>Plotting a function is often helpful to better understand what&amp;rsquo;s going on. Plotting curves in R base is simple by virtue of function curve. But how to draw curves using ggplot2?
That&amp;rsquo;s a little bit more complicated by can still be accomplished by 1-2 lines.
library(ggplot2)  Normal curve p &amp;lt;- ggplot(data = data.frame(x = c(-3, 3)), aes(x)) p + stat_function(fun = dnorm, n = 101)  stat_function is some kind of parallel function to curve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Squares maximize area - a visualization</title>
      <link>/2017/05/19/maximize_area/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/19/maximize_area/</guid>
      <description>An old story is that one of the farmer with a fence of some given length, say 20m. Now this farmer wants to put up his fence so that he claims the largest piece of land possible. What width (w) and height (h) should we pick?
Instead of a formal proof, let&amp;rsquo;s start with a visualization.
First, we need some packages.
library(tidyverse) library(gganimate) library(RColorBrewer) library(scales) library(knitr)  Now, let&amp;rsquo;s make up serveral ways to split up a rectengular piece of land.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A predictor&#39;s unique contribution - (visual) demonstration</title>
      <link>/2017/05/17/storks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/17/storks/</guid>
      <description>A well-known property of regression models is that they capture the unique contribution of a predictor. By &amp;ldquo;unique&amp;rdquo; we mean the effect of the predictor (on the criterion) if the other predictor(s) is/are held constant. A typical classroom example goes along the following lines.
All about storks  There&amp;rsquo;s a correlation between babies and storks. Counties with lots of storks enjoy large number of babies and v.v.
 However, I have children, I know the storks are not overly involved in that business, so says the teacher (polite laughters in the audience).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plotting true random numbers</title>
      <link>/2017/05/12/true_random/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/12/true_random/</guid>
      <description>knitr::opts_chunk$set(fig.align = &amp;quot;center&amp;quot;, out.width = &amp;quot;70%&amp;quot;, fig.asp = .61)  Every now and then, random numbers come in handy to demonstrate some statistical behavior. Of course, well-known appraoches are rnorm and friends. These functions are what is called pseudo random number generators, because they are not random at all, strictly speaking, but determined by some algorithm. An algorithm is a sort of creature that is 100% predictable once you know the input (and the details of the algorithm).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variance explained vs. variance blurred</title>
      <link>/2017/05/05/explained_variance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/05/explained_variance/</guid>
      <description>Frequently, someones says that some indicator variable X &amp;ldquo;explains&amp;rdquo; some proportion of some target variable, Y. What does this actually mean? By &amp;ldquo;mean&amp;rdquo; I am trying to find some intuition that &amp;ldquo;clicks&amp;rdquo; rather than citing the (well-known) formualas.
To start with, let&amp;rsquo;s load some packages and make up some random data.
library(tidyverse)  n_rows &amp;lt;- 100 set.seed(271828) df &amp;lt;- data_frame( exp_clean = rnorm(n = n_rows, mean = 2, sd = 1), cntrl_clean = rnorm(n = n_rows, mean = 0, sd = 1), exp_noisy = exp_clean + rnorm(n = n_rows, mean = 0, sd = 3), cntrl_noisy = cntrl_clean + rnorm(n = n_rows, mean = 0, sd = 3), ID = 1:n_rows)  Here, we drew 100 cases from the population of the &amp;ldquo;experimental group&amp;rdquo; (mue = 2) and 100 cases from the control group (mue = 0).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plotting skewed distributions</title>
      <link>/2017/04/19/skewed-distribs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/19/skewed-distribs/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s plot some skewed stuff, aehm, distributions!
Actually, the point I - initially - wanted to make is that in skewed distribution, don&amp;rsquo;t use means. Or at least, be very aware that (arithmetic) means can be grossly misleading. But for today, let&amp;rsquo;s focus on drawing skewed distributions.
Some packages:
library(tidyverse) library(fGarch) # for snorm  Some skewed distribution include:
 &amp;ldquo;polluted&amp;rdquo; normal distributions, ie., mixtures of two normals Exponential distributions Gamma distributions Beta distributions  One way to visualize them is to draw their curve, ie.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Error bars for interaction effects with nominal variables</title>
      <link>/2017/04/18/moderator-errorbars/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/18/moderator-errorbars/</guid>
      <description>Moderator effects (ie., interaction or synergy effects) are a topic of frequent interest in many sciences braches. A lot ink has been spilled over this topic (so did I, eg., here).
However, in that post I did now show how to visualize error in case of nominal (categorical) independent variable, and categorical moderator.
Luckily, visualization of this case is quite straight forward with ggplot2.
First, some data and packages to be loaded:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The two ggplot2-ways of plottings bars</title>
      <link>/2017/01/20/two_ways_barplots_with_ggplot2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/20/two_ways_barplots_with_ggplot2/</guid>
      <description>Bar plots, whereas not appropriate for means, are helpful for conveying impressions of frequencies, particularly relative frequencies, ie., proportions.
Intuition: Bar plots and histograms alike can be thought of as piles of Lego pieces, put onto each each other, where each Lego piece represents (is) one observation.
Presenting tables of frequencies are often not insightful to the eye. Bar plots are often much more accessible and present the story more clearly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing Interaction Effects with ggplot2</title>
      <link>/2017/01/17/vis_interaction_effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/17/vis_interaction_effects/</guid>
      <description>Moderator effects or interaction effect are a frequent topic of scientific endeavor. Put bluntly, such effects respond to the question whether the input variable X (predictor or independent variable IV) has an effect on the output variable (dependent variable DV) Y: &amp;ldquo;it depends&amp;rdquo;. More precisely, it depends on a second variable, M (Moderator).
More formally, a moderation effect can be summarized as follows:
 If the effect of X on Y depends on M, a moderator effect takes place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some musings on the validation of Satow&#39;s Extraversion questionnaire</title>
      <link>/2016/11/23/validation_extraversion_questionnaire/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/23/validation_extraversion_questionnaire/</guid>
      <description>Measuring personality traits is one of (the?) bread-and-butter business of psychologists, at least for quantitatively oriented ones. Literally, thousand of psychometric questionnaires exits. Measures abound. Extroversion, part of the Big Five personality theory approach, is one of the most widely used, and extensively scrutinized questionnaire tapping into human personality.
One rather new, but quite often used questionnaire, is Satow&amp;rsquo;s (2012) B5T. The reason for the popularity of this instrument is that it runs under a CC-licence - in contrast to the old ducks, which coute chere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing survey results data</title>
      <link>/2016/11/19/preparing_survey_data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/19/preparing_survey_data/</guid>
      <description>Analyzing survey results is a frequent endeavor (for some including me). Let&amp;rsquo;s not think about arguments whether and when surveys are useful or not (for some recent criticism see Briggs&amp;rsquo; book).
Typically, respondents circle some option ranging from &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t agree at all&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;completely agree&amp;rdquo; for each question (or &amp;ldquo;item&amp;rdquo;). Typically, four to six boxes are given where one is expected to tick one.
In this tutorial, I will discuss some typical steps to prepare the data for subsequent analyses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New bar stacking with ggplot 2.2.0</title>
      <link>/2016/11/13/improved_bar_stacking_ggplot2_220/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/13/improved_bar_stacking_ggplot2_220/</guid>
      <description>Recently, ggplot2 2.2.0 was released. Among other news, stacking bar plot was improved. Here is a short demonstration.
Load libraries
library(tidyverse) library(htmlTable)  &amp;hellip; and load data:
data &amp;lt;- read.csv(&amp;quot;https://osf.io/meyhp/?action=download&amp;quot;)  DOI for this piece of data is 10.17605/OSF.IO/4KGZH.
The data consists of results of a survey on extraversion and associated behavior.
Say, we would like to visualize the responsed to the extraversion items (there are 10 of them).
So, let&amp;rsquo;s see.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plotting survey results using `ggplot2`</title>
      <link>/2016/11/12/plotting_surveys/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/12/plotting_surveys/</guid>
      <description>Plotting (and more generally, analyzing) survey results is a frequent endeavor in many business environments. Let&amp;rsquo;s not think about arguments whether and when surveys are useful (for some recent criticism see Briggs&amp;rsquo; book).
Typically, respondents circle some option ranging from &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t agree at all&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;completely agree&amp;rdquo; for each question (or &amp;ldquo;item&amp;rdquo;). Typically, four to six boxes are given where one is expected to tick one.
In this tutorial, I will discuss some barplot type visualizations; the presentation is based on ggplot2 (within the R environment) .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to plot a &#39;percentage plot&#39; with ggplot2</title>
      <link>/2016/11/03/percentage_plot_ggplot2_v2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/03/percentage_plot_ggplot2_v2/</guid>
      <description>At times it is convenient to draw a frequency bar plot; at times we prefer not the bare frequencies but the proportions or the percentages per category. There are lots of ways doing so; let&amp;rsquo;s look at some ggplot2 ways.
First, let&amp;rsquo;s load some data.
data(tips, package = &amp;quot;reshape2&amp;quot;)  And the typical libraries.
library(dplyr) library(ggplot2) library(tidyr) library(scales) # for percentage scales  Way 1 tips %&amp;gt;% count(day) %&amp;gt;% mutate(perc = n / nrow(tips)) -&amp;gt; tips2 ggplot(tips2, aes(x = day, y = perc)) + geom_bar(stat = &amp;quot;identity&amp;quot;)  Way 2 ggplot(tips, aes(x = day)) + geom_bar(aes(y = (.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CLES plot</title>
      <link>/2016/10/17/cles-plot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/10/17/cles-plot/</guid>
      <description>In data analysis, we often ask &amp;ldquo;Do these two groups differ in the outcome variable&amp;rdquo;? Asking this question, a tacit assumption may be that the grouping variable is the cause of the difference in the outcome variable. For example, assume the two groups are &amp;ldquo;treatment group&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;control group&amp;rdquo;, and the outcome variable is &amp;ldquo;pain reduction&amp;rdquo;.
A typical approach would be to report the strenght of the difference by help of Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code example for plotting boxplots instead of mean bars</title>
      <link>/2016/09/22/use-boxplots/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/09/22/use-boxplots/</guid>
      <description>On a recent psychology conference I had the impression that psychologists keep preferring to show mean values, but appear less interested in more detailled plots such as the boxplot. Plots like the boxplot are richer in information, but not more difficult to perceive.
For those who would like to have an easy starter on how to visualize more informative plots (more than mean bars), here is a suggestion:
# install.pacakges(&amp;quot;Ecdat&amp;quot;) library(Ecdat) # dataset on extramarital affairs data(Fair) str(Fair)  ## &#39;data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plot of mean with exact numbers using ggplot2</title>
      <link>/2016/08/30/plot_dot_means/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/08/30/plot_dot_means/</guid>
      <description>Often, both in academic research and more business-driven data analysis, we want to compare some (two in many cases) means. We will not discuss here that friends should not let friends plot barplots. Following the advise of Cleveland&amp;rsquo;s seminal book we will plot the means using dots, not bars.
However, at times we do not simply want the diagram, but we (or someone) is interested in the bare, plain, naked, exact numbers too.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shading multiple areas under normal curve</title>
      <link>/2016/08/30/shade_normal_curve/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/08/30/shade_normal_curve/</guid>
      <description>When plotting a normal curve, it is often helpful to color (or shade) some segments. For example, often we might want to indicate whether an absolute value is greater than 2.
How can we achieve this with ggplot2? Here is one way.
First, load packages and define some constants. Specifically, we define mean, sd, and start/end (z-) value of the area we want to shade. And your favorite color is defined.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple way to plot a normal distribution with ggplot2</title>
      <link>/2016/08/30/normal_curve_ggplot2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/08/30/normal_curve_ggplot2/</guid>
      <description>Plotting a normal distribution is something needed in a variety of situation: Explaining to students (or professors) the basic of statistics; convincing your clients that a t-Test is (not) the right approach to the problem, or pondering on the vicissitudes of life&amp;hellip;
If you like ggplot2, you may have wondered what the easiest way is to plot a normal curve with ggplot2?
Here is one:
library(cowplot)  ## Loading required package: ggplot2  ## ## Attaching package: &#39;cowplot&#39;  ## The following object is masked from &#39;package:ggplot2&#39;: ## ## ggsave  p1 &amp;lt;- ggplot(data = data.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>