<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/data/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>OECD Wellbeing dataset (2016)</title>
      <link>/2018/10/16/oecd-wellbeing-dataset-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/16/oecd-wellbeing-dataset-2016/</guid>
      <description>Packages We will need the following packages in this post:
library(mosaic) library(knitr) library(DT)  The OECD wellbeing study series The OECD keeps measuring the wellbeing (and associated variables) among its members states.
On the project website, the OECD states:
 In recent years, concerns have emerged regarding the fact that macro-economic statistics, such as GDP, don’t provide a sufficiently detailed picture of the living conditions that ordinary people experience. While these concerns were already evident during the years of strong growth and good economic performance that characterised the early part of the decade, the financial and economic crisis has further amplified them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data sets suitable for business case studies</title>
      <link>/2017/11/29/data-sets-suitable-for-business-case-studies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/29/data-sets-suitable-for-business-case-studies/</guid>
      <description>Data sets are a useful didactical tool for demontrating procedure of data analysis. For business audiences, business type data sets propose themselves. This post curates a list of data sets I find useful for this purpose.
 Boston Housing  R package: MASS Data access case study  NYC flights data  R package: nyflights13 Data access case study  Wine Quality  R package: ??? Data access - Red wine case study  tiping data  R package: reshape2 Data access  Diamonds  R package: ggplot2 case study   Curated lists of data sets  vincentarelbundock    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Package &#39;pradadata&#39; on Github - feature social science data</title>
      <link>/2017/11/07/pradadata/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/07/pradadata/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve put a package on Github featureing some social science data set. Some data came from official sites; my contribution was to clear &amp;lsquo;em up, and render comfortably accessable for automatic inquiry (nice header lines, no special enconding, flat csvs&amp;hellip;.). In other cases it&amp;rsquo;s unpublished data collected by friends, students of mine or myself.
Let&amp;rsquo;s check its contents using a function by Maiasaura from this SO post.
library(pradadata) lsp &amp;lt;- function (package, all.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data, machine-friendly, of the 2017 German federal elections</title>
      <link>/2017/10/30/de-elec-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/30/de-elec-data/</guid>
      <description>On September 2017, the 19. German Bundestag has been elected. As of this writing, the parties are still busy sorting out whether they want to part of the government, with whom, and maybe whether they even want to form a government at all. This post is about providing the data in machine friendly form, and in English language.
All data presented in this post regarding this (and previous) elections are published by the Bundeswahlleiter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dataset &#39;performance in stats test&#39;</title>
      <link>/2017/01/27/data_test_inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/27/data_test_inference/</guid>
      <description>This posts shows data cleaning and preparation for a data set on a statistics test (NHST inference). Data is published under a CC-licence, see here.
Data was collected 2015 to 2017 in statistics courses at the FOM university in different places in Germany. Several colleagues helped to collect the data. Thanks a lot! Now let&amp;rsquo;s enjoy the outcome (and make it freely available to all).
Raw N is 743. The test consists of 40 items which are framed as propositions; students are asked to respond with either &amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;false&amp;rdquo; to each item.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The effect of a status symbol on success in online dating: an experimental study (data paper)</title>
      <link>/2016/08/27/data_status_dating/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/08/27/data_status_dating/</guid>
      <description>This article has been published at The Winnower, it is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and redistribution in any medium, provided that the original author and source are credited.
Data can be accessed here.
Access the paper here.
CITATION: Sebastian Sauer, Alexander Wolff, The effect of a status symbol on success in online dating: an experimental study (data paper), The Winnower 3:e147241.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>