<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>rmd on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/rmd/</link>
    <description>Recent content in rmd on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/rmd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Generating mass reports using Rmarkdown in R</title>
      <link>/2018/12/19/generating-mass-reports/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/19/generating-mass-reports/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes, one document must be recreated in similar fashions a lot of times. For instance, invoices to customers, grading schemes for students, progress reports in projects, and so on. In this post, I demonstrate one way to do that in R using RMarkdown.
Specifically, it is assumed that there’s a tabular data set, where each row refers to a document instance (eg., a mail or report to one given person), and each column holds the variables to appear in each reports (see examples below).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two r plots side by sind in a Rmd-File - UPDATE</title>
      <link>/2017/10/12/two-r-plots-side-by-sind-in-a-rmd-file/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/12/two-r-plots-side-by-sind-in-a-rmd-file/</guid>
      <description>UPDATE 2018-12-03
Thanks to a comment by Katharina Hees and Joyce, I know know how to plot two images side by side in an Rmd file.
I kept wondering who to plot two R plots side by side (ie., in one “row”) in a .Rmd chunk. Here’s a way, well actually a number of ways, some good, some … not.
library(tidyverse) library(gridExtra) library(grid) library(png) library(downloader) library(grDevices) data(mtcars) Plots from ggplot Say, you have two plots from ggplot2, and you would like them to put them next to each other, side by side (not underneath each other):</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>