<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dataviz on Data Se</title>
    <link>/categories/dataviz/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dataviz on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/dataviz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing around with dumbbell plots</title>
      <link>/2018/05/23/playing-around-with-dumbbell-plots/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/23/playing-around-with-dumbbell-plots/</guid>
      <description>Dumbbell plots can be used to show differences between two groups. Bob Rudis demonstrated a beautiful application of such plots using ggplot2 board methods.
In this plot, I will explain or comment his code, and adapt a few changes.
First, load some packages.
pacman::p_load(tidyverse, ggalt) Let’s make up some data. Tip: Make up some data conveniently in Excel, copy it to the clipboard, and then paste it as tribble (see below) into R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing around with dataviz: Comparing distributions between groups</title>
      <link>/2018/05/18/playing-around-dataviz-comparing-distributions-between-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/18/playing-around-dataviz-comparing-distributions-between-groups/</guid>
      <description>What’ a nice way to display distributional differences between a (larger) number of groups? Boxplots is one way to go. In addition, the raw data may be shown as dots, but should be demphasized. Third, a trend or big picture comparing the groups will make sense in some cases.
Ok, based on this reasoning, let’s do som visualizing. Let’s load some data (movies), and the usual culprits of packages.
library(tidyverse) library(mosaic) data(movies, package = &amp;quot;ggplot2movies&amp;quot;) Now let’s add a variable for decade as year is too fine grained.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing around with dataviz: Showing correlations</title>
      <link>/2018/05/18/playing-around-with-dataviz-showing-correlations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/18/playing-around-with-dataviz-showing-correlations/</guid>
      <description>In this plot, we are looking into some ways of displaying association between (two) quantitative variables, aka correlation. Our goal is to present a rich representation of the correlation.
Let’s take the dataset flights as an example.
data(flights, package = &amp;quot;nycflights13&amp;quot;) library(tidyverse) library(viridis) flights %&amp;gt;% filter(arr_delay &amp;lt; 100, dep_delay &amp;lt; 100) %&amp;gt;% ggplot(aes(x = dep_delay, y = arr_delay, color = origin)) + geom_point(alpha = .01) + geom_smooth(se = FALSE, color = &amp;quot;grey20&amp;quot;) + geom_rug() + facet_wrap(~origin) + scale_color_viridis_d() ## `geom_smooth()` using method = &amp;#39;gam&amp;#39; and formula &amp;#39;y ~ s(x, bs = &amp;quot;cs&amp;quot;)&amp;#39; Points are not the only geom that make sense here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Showcase of Viridis, maps, and ggcounty</title>
      <link>/2018/05/18/showcase-of-viridis-maps-and-ggounty/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/18/showcase-of-viridis-maps-and-ggounty/</guid>
      <description>This posts shows how easy it can be to build an visually pleasing plot. We will use hrbrmster’s ggcounty, which is an R package at this Github repo. Graphics engine is as mostly in my plots, Hadley Wickhams ggplot. All build on R. Standing on shoulders…
Disclaimer: This example heavily draws on hrbrmster example on this page. All credit is due to Rudy, and those on whose work he built up on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick intro to geo plotting</title>
      <link>/2018/05/17/quick-intro-to-geo-plotting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/17/quick-intro-to-geo-plotting/</guid>
      <description>Geo plotting can be simple; at least in its basic form. Let’s review an example using data from GADM.
GADM provides maps for many (all?) countries of the world; not only the country borders but even administrative border lines an a finder scale.
It comes very handy that the map (geo) can be downloaded as R data files:
data_path &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;https://biogeo.ucdavis.edu/data/gadm3.6/Rsf/gadm36_DEU_2_sf.rds&amp;quot; Load some packages:
library(sf) library(tidyverse) library(downloader) Download the maps data:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing a logistic regression the easy way</title>
      <link>/2018/01/23/visualizing-a-logistic-regression-the-easy-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/23/visualizing-a-logistic-regression-the-easy-way/</guid>
      <description>Let’s visualize a GLM (logistic regression).
First laod some data:
data(tips, package = &amp;quot;reshape2&amp;quot;) Compute a glm:
glm_tips &amp;lt;- glm(sex ~ tip, data = tips, family = &amp;quot;binomial&amp;quot;) Plot the model using mosaic:
library(mosaic) plotModel(glm_tips) The curve does not look really s-typed (ogive) but that’s ok because the data suggest not a strong trend. The plot is not very beautiful either, but hey - it’s quick to produce 😁.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive diagrams in lieu of shiny?</title>
      <link>/2017/11/27/interactive-diagrams-in-lieu-of-shiny/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/27/interactive-diagrams-in-lieu-of-shiny/</guid>
      <description>One frequent use of the Shiny server software is displaying interactive data diagrams. The pro of using Shiny is the great flexibility; much more than “just graphics” can be done. Basically Shiny provides a flexible GUI for your R program. But if you simply aiming at displaying or exploring some data interactively, a much simplor approach may do it for you; there are some nice libraries available in R for that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Great dataviz examples in rstats</title>
      <link>/2017/11/20/great-dataviz-examples-in-rstats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/20/great-dataviz-examples-in-rstats/</guid>
      <description>Here come some stunning examples of data visualizations, all built with R. R code of each diagram is available at the source. Enjoy! #beautiful.
UPDATE: I&amp;rsquo;ve included links to the R source!
Plotting geo maps along with subplots in ggplot2 I like this one by Ilya Kashnitsky:
Similarly, by the same author:
Source
Great work, @ikashnitsky!
Cirlize (Chord) diagrams Plotting association in a circular form yields aesthetic examples of diagrams, see the following examples</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>