<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>r on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in r on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk - Predictors of AfD party success in the 2017 elections. A Bayesian modeling  approach</title>
      <link>/2018/09/02/predictors-of-afd-party-success-in-the-2017-elections-a-bayesian-modeling-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/02/predictors-of-afd-party-success-in-the-2017-elections-a-bayesian-modeling-approach/</guid>
      <description>Talk at DGPs 2018.
Get slides here http://data-se.netlify.com/slides/afd_dgps2018/afd_dgps2018.html</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Showcase of Viridis, maps, and ggcounty</title>
      <link>/2018/05/18/showcase-of-viridis-maps-and-ggounty/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/18/showcase-of-viridis-maps-and-ggounty/</guid>
      <description>This posts shows how easy it can be to build an visually pleasing plot. We will use hrbrmster’s ggcounty, which is an R package at this Github repo. Graphics engine is as mostly in my plots, Hadley Wickhams ggplot. All build on R. Standing on shoulders…
Disclaimer: This example heavily draws on hrbrmster example on this page. All credit is due to Rudy, and those on whose work he built up on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick intro to geo plotting</title>
      <link>/2018/05/17/quick-intro-to-geo-plotting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/17/quick-intro-to-geo-plotting/</guid>
      <description>Geo plotting can be simple; at least in its basic form. Let’s review an example using data from GADM.
GADM provides maps for many (all?) countries of the world; not only the country borders but even administrative border lines an a finder scale.
It comes very handy that the map (geo) can be downloaded as R data files:
data_path &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;https://biogeo.ucdavis.edu/data/gadm3.6/Rsf/gadm36_DEU_2_sf.rds&amp;quot; Load some packages:
library(sf) library(tidyverse) library(downloader) Download the maps data:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One-way ANOVA power analysis</title>
      <link>/2018/04/11/one-way-anova-power-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/11/one-way-anova-power-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Computing or estimating power is a very useful procedure in order to weigh the reliability of study results.
One frequent procedure in inferential statistics is the ANOVA, with the simplest form being the one-way ANOVA. This post shows how to compute power for this test.
What’s the effect size? The first thing to not is that there is no such thing as “power” - in the sense that a sample or a test would have “its power”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parse libraries from R project</title>
      <link>/2018/04/11/parse-libraries-from-r-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/11/parse-libraries-from-r-project/</guid>
      <description>Having written a larger R project is may be of interest which packages have been used. As I did not find a read-to-use package, a colleague of mine - Norman Markgraf - came up with a nice solution. In this post, I build on his solution to provide a function that suits my needs of today:
@Norman: Thanks for your great idea!
First, some libraries:
library(tidyverse) library(bibtex) library(testthat) Then, here is some path of an R project where we want to parse all rmd files:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metrics for readability of slide decks for teaching</title>
      <link>/2018/04/09/metrics-for-readability-of-slide-decks-for-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/09/metrics-for-readability-of-slide-decks-for-teaching/</guid>
      <description>Some thoughts on the “quality” of slide decks used in teaching: How many visuals are there? How much text is squeezed on a slide? What’s the average word and sentence length? How much buzz words and complicated jargon is present?
Let’s have an initial look at some meaures in that regard. Hey, this post is just playing around a little. We will work with this slide deck, published under CC-BY 3, with parts as GNU - so all “open” in short.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why &#34;n-1&#34; in empirical variance? A simulation.</title>
      <link>/2018/03/24/why-n-1-in-empirical-variance-a-simulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/24/why-n-1-in-empirical-variance-a-simulation/</guid>
      <description>It is well-known that the empirical variance underestimates the population variance. Specifically, the empirical variance is defined as: \(var_{emp} = \frac{\sum_i (x_i - \bar{x})^2}{n-1}\). But why \(n-1\), why not just \(n\), as intuition (of some) dictates? Put shortly, as the variance of a sample tends to underestimate the population variance we have to inflate it artificially, to enlarge it, that’s why we do put a smaller number (the “n-1”) in the denominator, resulting in a larger value of the whole fraction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Error bars for interaction effects with nominal variables</title>
      <link>/2017/04/18/moderator-errorbars/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/18/moderator-errorbars/</guid>
      <description>Moderator effects (ie., interaction or synergy effects) are a topic of frequent interest in many sciences braches. A lot ink has been spilled over this topic (so did I, eg., here).
However, in that post I did now show how to visualize error in case of nominal (categorical) independent variable, and categorical moderator.
Luckily, visualization of this case is quite straight forward with ggplot2.
First, some data and packages to be loaded:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>