<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>reproducibility on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/reproducibility/</link>
    <description>Recent content in reproducibility on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/reproducibility/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides for my workshop on Markdown and Git</title>
      <link>/2019/09/09/slides-for-my-workshop-on-markdown-and-git/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/09/slides-for-my-workshop-on-markdown-and-git/</guid>
      <description>Here are my slides for my Workshop on Markdown and Git (2019-09-16). Note that you need to be online to render the slides (due to heavy use of JS).
The Rmd source code (master file) can be found here.
The PDF version of the slides can be found here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to document a conference talk in citation manager software</title>
      <link>/2019/06/28/how-to-document-a-conference-talk-in-citation-manager-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/06/28/how-to-document-a-conference-talk-in-citation-manager-software/</guid>
      <description>There are several popular citation manager software packages around. I used to work with Mendeley in class, but I stopped using it since it was acquired by El$sevier. Luckily there are good alternatives around, particularly Zotero. Zotero features a Word (MS Word, Libre Word) plugin, which is a must have for many of us. The more technically inclined folks will use Bibtex. Good news is that Zotero syncs it Library to Bibtex.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A clean sessionInfo page</title>
      <link>/2019/01/14/a-clean-sessioninfo-page/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/14/a-clean-sessioninfo-page/</guid>
      <description>Writing a technical or academic report, or even a presentation, it is sensible to render the (R) code in such a writing reproducible. Same thing applies when asking for help at StackOverflow: you’ll be asked for a reprex.
One aspect for rendering a report reproducible is to include details on the version of packages needed. The well-known command sessionInf() provides the building blocks for that. However, the output of that function can feel verbose, and it consumes a lot of space.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible academic writing with RMarkdown - Talk at DGPs 2018</title>
      <link>/2018/09/03/reproducible-academic-writing-with-rmarkdown-talk-at-dgps-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/03/reproducible-academic-writing-with-rmarkdown-talk-at-dgps-2018/</guid>
      <description>Talk at DGPs 2018.
Get slides here: http://data-se.netlify.com/slides/rmd-writing/rmd-writing_dgps2018.html.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This blog now has a DOI</title>
      <link>/2017/05/04/doi_added/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/04/doi_added/</guid>
      <description>A DOI is useful feature to any electronic document. What the ID number in your passport is to you is the DOI to a document. It simply helps to make sure you address the &amp;ldquo;object&amp;rdquo; you want to address.
Similarly, there may exists several &amp;ldquo;Joachims Zwiwwelkoecks&amp;rdquo; in this world (well, it may or may not be the case). However, if any of this person gets his (or her) unique ID (could by a simple number), then we would in principle always be certain that we address the right person.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools for Academic Writing - Comparison</title>
      <link>/2017/04/26/writing_tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/26/writing_tools/</guid>
      <description>Many tools exist for academic writing including the notorious W.O.R.D.; but many more are out there. Let&#39;s have a look at those tools, and discuss what&#39;s important (what we expect the tool to deliver, eg., beautiful typesetting).
Typical tools for academic writing   MS Word: A &amp;ldquo;classical&amp;rdquo; choice, relied upon by myriads of white collar workers&amp;hellip; I myself have used it extensively for academic writing; the main advantage being its simplicity, that is, well, everybody knows it, and knows more or less how to handle it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>