<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Simulation on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/simulation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Simulation on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/simulation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulating a correlation matrix.</title>
      <link>/2018/05/18/simulating-a-correlation-matrix/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/18/simulating-a-correlation-matrix/</guid>
      <description>Simulation based inference is a powerful tool as it lets you derive population estimates without having to solve difficult equations. As a more advanced example for simulation, consider the following situation. You are interested in the correlation of air time and delay of planes. More precisely you assume that this correlation is the same for different carriers (airlines). In other words, the (absolute) difference between all different pairs of correlation coefficient is zero, according to the hypothesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why is the sample mean a good point estimator of the population mean? A simulation and some thoughts.</title>
      <link>/2018/05/18/why-is-the-sample-mean-a-good-point-estimator-of-the-population-mean-a-simulation-and-some-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/18/why-is-the-sample-mean-a-good-point-estimator-of-the-population-mean-a-simulation-and-some-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>It is frequently stated that the sample mean is a good or even the best point estimator of the according population value. But why is that? In this post we are trying to get an intuition by using simulation inference methods.
Assume you played throwing coins with some one at some dark corner. “Some one” throws the coin 10 times, and wins 8 times (he was betting on heads, but that’s only for the sake of the story).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The effect of sample on p-values. A simulation.</title>
      <link>/2017/04/13/pvalue_sample_size/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/13/pvalue_sample_size/</guid>
      <description>It is well-known that the notorious p-values is sensitive to sample size: The larger the sample, the more bound the p-value is to fall below the magic number of .05.
Of course, the p-value is also a function of the effect size, eg., the distance between two means and the respective variances. But still, the p-values tends to become significant in the face of larges samples, and non-significant otherwise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crashkurs zur Erstellung von Barplots für Umfrage-Daten</title>
      <link>/2016/11/13/crashkurs_barplots/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/13/crashkurs_barplots/</guid>
      <description>Eine recht häufige Art von Daten in der Wirtschaft kommen von Umfragen in der Belegschaft. Diese Daten gilt es dann aufzubereiten und graphisch wiederzugeben. Dafür gibt dieser Post einige grundlegende Hinweise. Grundwissen mit R setzen wir voraus :-)
Eine ausführlichere Beschreibung hier sich z.B. hier.
Packages laden Nicht vergessen: Ein Computerprogramm (z.B. ein R-Package) kann man nur dann laden, wenn man es vorher installier hat (aber es reicht, das Programm/R-Package einmal zu installieren).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some thoughts (and simulation) on overfitting</title>
      <link>/2016/11/13/overfitting_simulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/13/overfitting_simulation/</guid>
      <description>Overfitting is a common problem in data analysis. Some go as far as saying that &amp;ldquo;most of&amp;rdquo; published research is false (John Ionnadis); overfitting being one, maybe central, problem of it. In this post, we explore some aspects on the notion of overfitting.
Assume we have 10 metric variables v (personality/health/behavior/gene indicator variables), and, say, 10 variables for splitting up subgroups (aged vs. young, female vs. male, etc.), so 10 dichotomic variables.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>