<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>simulation on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/simulation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in simulation on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/simulation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Birth Weight Paradoxon -- A simulation for intuition</title>
      <link>/2020/06/11/birth-weight-paradoxon-a-simulation-for-intuition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/11/birth-weight-paradoxon-a-simulation-for-intuition/</guid>
      <description>Load packages library(tidyverse) library(ggdag) library(gt) library(dagitty)  The Birth Weight Paradoxon The Birth Weight Paradoxon have kept on puzzling researchers for decades, as Pearl notes here.
In [Wikipedia], this paradox is characterized as such:
 Traditionally, babies weighing less than a certain amount (which varies between countries) have been classified as having low birth weight. In a given population, low birth weight babies have a significantly higher mortality rate than others; thus, populations with a higher rate of low birth weights typically also have higher rates of child mortality than other populations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Correlation is intransitive -- a simulation</title>
      <link>/2020/06/11/correlation-is-intransitive-simulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/11/correlation-is-intransitive-simulation/</guid>
      <description>Load packages library(tidyverse) library(MASS) library(rockchalk)  Correlation is not transitive It has probably been known since a long time that correlation is not transitive. However, in practice the error of assuming that correlation would be transitive is some times committed.
For example, Nassim Taleb has pointed out that (some or all) psychologists would commit such an error when they state “genes are correlated with IQ, IQ is correlated with performance, hence genes are correlated with performance”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulating values according to some distribution</title>
      <link>/2020/06/05/simulating-values-according-to-some-distribution/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/05/simulating-values-according-to-some-distribution/</guid>
      <description>Load packages library(tidyverse) library(mosaic)  What’s a Monte Carlo simulation? A Monte Carlo Simulation is a numeric approach to solving difficult problems. Instead of having an analytic way of solving the problem, one just says “ok, let’s try it out and see what happens”.
 Coin flip distribution Simalatin a single coin flip (Bernoulli) distribution can be achieved like this:
rflip() #&amp;gt; #&amp;gt; Flipping 1 coin [ Prob(Heads) = 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulation based inference for non-parametric tests, and a trick</title>
      <link>/2020/06/05/sbi-nonparametric/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/05/sbi-nonparametric/</guid>
      <description>Load packages library(tidyverse) library(mosaic)  Data data(&amp;quot;tips&amp;quot;, package = &amp;quot;reshape2&amp;quot;)  Non-parametric tests and simulation based inference Simulation-based inference (SBI) is an old tool that has seen a surge in research interest in recent years probably due to the large amount of computational powers at the hands of researchers.
SBI is less prone to violations of assumptions, particularly with distributional assumptions. This is because inference is not based on the idea that some variable follows a – for example – normal distribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chi-squared test using simulation based inference</title>
      <link>/2020/06/04/chi-squared-test-using-simulation-based-inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/04/chi-squared-test-using-simulation-based-inference/</guid>
      <description>Load packages library(tidyverse)  Simulation based inference Simulation based inference (SBI) is an elegant way of subsuming a wide array of statistical (inference) methods under one umbrella. In addition, its simple thereby helping learners getting to the grips.
Here’s a summary of the central ideas.
However, this post does not aim at explaining simulation based inference, which is done elsewhere.
 Testing the association of two categorical variables One application of statistical tests – simulation based or classical – is testing the association of two categorical variables.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Folien für den Workshop zur simulationsbasierten Inferenz, 2020-02-05</title>
      <link>/2020/02/02/folien-f%C3%BCr-den-workshop-zur-simulationsbasierten-inferenz-2020-02-05/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/02/folien-f%C3%BCr-den-workshop-zur-simulationsbasierten-inferenz-2020-02-05/</guid>
      <description>   Workshop zu simulationsbasierter Inferenz Die Folien für meinen Workshop zur simulationsbasierten Inferenz finden sich hier.
Die PDF-Version findet sich hier.
Der Quellcode liegt hier.
Die Folien sind unter CC-BY 4.0 De lizensiert.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A stochastic problem by Warren Buffet solved with simulation</title>
      <link>/2019/04/04/a-stochastic-problem-by-warren-buffet-solved-with-simulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/04/04/a-stochastic-problem-by-warren-buffet-solved-with-simulation/</guid>
      <description>This post presents a stochastic problem, with application to financial theory taken from this magazine article. Some say the problem goes back to Warren Buffett. Thanks to my colleague Norman Markgraf, who pointed it out to me.
Assume there are two coins. One is fair, one is loaded. The loaded coin has a bias of 60-40. Now, the question is: How many coin flips do you need to be “sure enough” (say, 95%) that you found the loaded coin?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some musings on the logistic map</title>
      <link>/2018/06/19/some-musings-on-the-logistic-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/19/some-musings-on-the-logistic-map/</guid>
      <description>The logistic map is a well-known and simple growth model that is defined by the iterative equation
\[x_{t+1} = 4rx_t(1-t_t)\],
where \(r\) is a parameter that can be thought of as a fertility and reproduction rate of the population. The allowed values of \(x\) range between 0 an 1 inclusively, where 0 means the population is extinct. The maximum of 1 can be interpreted as the ecological carrying capacity of the system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulating a correlation matrix.</title>
      <link>/2018/05/18/simulating-a-correlation-matrix/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/18/simulating-a-correlation-matrix/</guid>
      <description>Simulation based inference is a powerful tool as it lets you derive population estimates without having to solve difficult equations. As a more advanced example for simulation, consider the following situation. You are interested in the correlation of air time and delay of planes. More precisely you assume that this correlation is the same for different carriers (airlines). In other words, the (absolute) difference between all different pairs of correlation coefficient is zero, according to the hypothesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why is the sample mean a good point estimator of the population mean? A simulation and some thoughts.</title>
      <link>/2018/05/18/why-is-the-sample-mean-a-good-point-estimator-of-the-population-mean-a-simulation-and-some-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/18/why-is-the-sample-mean-a-good-point-estimator-of-the-population-mean-a-simulation-and-some-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>It is frequently stated that the sample mean is a good or even the best point estimator of the according population value. But why is that? In this post we are trying to get an intuition by using simulation inference methods.
Assume you played throwing coins with some one at some dark corner. “Some one” throws the coin 10 times, and wins 8 times (the guy was betting on heads, but that’s only for the sake of the story).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The effect of sample on p-values. A simulation.</title>
      <link>/2017/04/13/pvalue_sample_size/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/13/pvalue_sample_size/</guid>
      <description>It is well-known that the notorious p-values is sensitive to sample size: The larger the sample, the more bound the p-value is to fall below the magic number of .05.
Of course, the p-value is also a function of the effect size, eg., the distance between two means and the respective variances. But still, the p-values tends to become significant in the face of larges samples, and non-significant otherwise.
Theoretically, quite simple and well understood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crashkurs zur Erstellung von Barplots für Umfrage-Daten</title>
      <link>/2016/11/13/crashkurs_barplots/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/13/crashkurs_barplots/</guid>
      <description>Eine recht häufige Art von Daten in der Wirtschaft kommen von Umfragen in der Belegschaft. Diese Daten gilt es dann aufzubereiten und graphisch wiederzugeben. Dafür gibt dieser Post einige grundlegende Hinweise. Grundwissen mit R setzen wir voraus :-)
Eine ausführlichere Beschreibung hier sich z.B. hier.
Packages laden Nicht vergessen: Ein Computerprogramm (z.B. ein R-Package) kann man nur dann laden, wenn man es vorher installier hat (aber es reicht, das Programm/R-Package einmal zu installieren).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some thoughts (and simulation) on overfitting</title>
      <link>/2016/11/13/overfitting_simulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/13/overfitting_simulation/</guid>
      <description>Overfitting is a common problem in data analysis. Some go as far as saying that &amp;ldquo;most of&amp;rdquo; published research is false (John Ionnadis); overfitting being one, maybe central, problem of it. In this post, we explore some aspects on the notion of overfitting.
Assume we have 10 metric variables v (personality/health/behavior/gene indicator variables), and, say, 10 variables for splitting up subgroups (aged vs. young, female vs. male, etc.), so 10 dichotomic variables.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>