<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>politics on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/politics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in politics on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Poster: A Bayes model of AfD party success</title>
      <link>/2019/01/24/poster-a-bayes-model-of-afd-party-success/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/24/poster-a-bayes-model-of-afd-party-success/</guid>
      <description>At the Dozentenmeeting 2019 of the FOM Hochschule, I presented a poster of an analysis of the AfD election success, based on a Bayes multi level regression.
The poster can be downloaded here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Populism in tweets of German politicians</title>
      <link>/2017/11/01/afd01/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/01/afd01/</guid>
      <description>The last months (years? since ever???) have seen a surge in populism and a rise in nationalism. Not only in Russia, the United States, Turkey, but also in some EU countries the ghost of nationalism-populism seems to be marching and gaining ground.
As to Germany, in September 24, 2017, the 19. German federal elections took place. The newly founded alt-right AfD (Alternative for Deutschland) has made a leap and moved in the Bundestag.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data, machine-friendly, of the 2017 German federal elections</title>
      <link>/2017/10/30/de-elec-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/30/de-elec-data/</guid>
      <description>On September 2017, the 19. German Bundestag has been elected. As of this writing, the parties are still busy sorting out whether they want to part of the government, with whom, and maybe whether they even want to form a government at all. This post is about providing the data in machine friendly form, and in English language.
All data presented in this post regarding this (and previous) elections are published by the Bundeswahlleiter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping foreigner ratio to AfD election results in the German Wahlkreise</title>
      <link>/2017/10/22/afd-map-foreigners/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/22/afd-map-foreigners/</guid>
      <description>In a previous post, we have shed some light on the idea that populism - as manifested in AfD election results - is associated with socioeconomic deprivation, be it subjective or objective. We found some supporting pattern in the data, although that hypothesis is far from being complete; ie., most of the variance remained unexplained.
In this post, we test the hypothesis that AfD election results are negatively associated with the proportion of foreign nationals in a Wahlkreis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping foreigner ratio to AfD election results in the German Wahlkreise</title>
      <link>/2017/10/22/mapping-foreigner-ratio-to-afd-election-results-in-the-german-wahlkreise/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/22/mapping-foreigner-ratio-to-afd-election-results-in-the-german-wahlkreise/</guid>
      <description>In a previous post, we have shed some light on the idea that populism - as manifested in AfD election results - is associated with socioeconomic deprivation, be it subjective or objective. We found some supporting pattern in the data, although that hypothesis is far from being complete; ie., most of the variance remained unexplained.
In this post, we test the hypothesis that AfD election results are negatively associated with the proportion of foreign nationals in a Wahlkreis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping unemployment ratio to AfD election results in German Wahlkreise</title>
      <link>/2017/10/10/afd-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/10/afd-map/</guid>
      <description>There is the idea that the alt-right German party AfD is followed by those who are deprived of chances, thoses of fearing to falling down the social ladder, and so on. Let&amp;rsquo;s test this hypothesis. No, I am not thinking on hypothesis testing, p-values, and stuff. Rather, let&amp;rsquo;s color a map of German election districts (Wahlkreise) according to whether the area is poor AND the AfD gained a lot of votes (and vice versa: the area is rich AND the AfD gained relatively few votes).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping unemployment rate to German district areas</title>
      <link>/2017/10/09/unemp-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/09/unemp-map/</guid>
      <description>A chloropleth map is a geographic map where statistical information are mapped to certain areas. Let&amp;rsquo;s plot such a chloropleth map in this post.
Packages library(sf) library(stringr) library(tidyverse) library(readxl)  Geo data Best place to get German geo data is from the &amp;ldquo;Bundesamt für Kartografie und Geodäsie (BKG)&amp;rdquo;. One may basically use the data for a purposes unless it is against the law. I have downloaded the data 2017-10-09. More specifically, we are looking at the &amp;ldquo;Verwaltungsgebiete&amp;rdquo; (vg), that is, the administrative areas of the country, ie.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>