<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Knitr on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/knitr/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Knitr on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/knitr/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Yart - Yet Another Markdown Report Template</title>
      <link>/2017/11/15/yart/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/15/yart/</guid>
      <description>It would be useful to have a RMarkdown template for typical (academic) reports such as class assigments and bachelor/master thesises. The LaTeX class &amp;ldquo;report&amp;rdquo; provides a suitable format for that. This package provides a simple wrapper around this class built on the standard pandoc template.
Thanks to Yart, ie, this package leans on earlier work by Aaron Wolen in his pandoc-letter repository, and extends it for use from R via the rmarkdown package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two R plot side by side in .Rmd-Files</title>
      <link>/2017/10/12/two-plots-rmd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/12/two-plots-rmd/</guid>
      <description>I kept wondering who to plot two R plots side by side (ie., in one &amp;ldquo;row&amp;rdquo;) in a .Rmd chunk. Here&amp;rsquo;s a way, well actually a number of ways, some good, some &amp;hellip; not.
library(tidyverse) library(gridExtra) library(grid) library(png) library(downloader) library(grDevices) data(mtcars)  Plots from ggplot Say, you have two plots from ggplot2, and you would like them to put them next to each other, side by side (not underneath each other):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two r plots side by sind in a Rmd-File - UPDATE</title>
      <link>/2017/10/12/two-r-plots-side-by-sind-in-a-rmd-file/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/12/two-r-plots-side-by-sind-in-a-rmd-file/</guid>
      <description>UPDATE 2018-12-03
Thanks to a comment by Katharina Hees and Joyce, I know know how to plot two images side by side in an Rmd file.
I kept wondering who to plot two R plots side by side (ie., in one “row”) in a .Rmd chunk. Here’s a way, well actually a number of ways, some good, some … not.
library(tidyverse) library(gridExtra) library(grid) library(png) library(downloader) library(grDevices) data(mtcars) Plots from ggplot Say, you have two plots from ggplot2, and you would like them to put them next to each other, side by side (not underneath each other):</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>