<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>modeling on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/modeling/</link>
    <description>Recent content in modeling on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/modeling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Spell out your model explicitly</title>
      <link>/2020/06/10/spell-out-your-model-explicitly/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/10/spell-out-your-model-explicitly/</guid>
      <description>Load packages library(tidyverse) library(hrbrthemes) library(MASS) library(moments)  Why you should spell out your model explicitly Often, assumptions of widely used models, such as linear models, appear opaque. Why is heteroscedasticity important? Where is a list of the model assumptions I need to consider?
As it turns out, there are straight forward answers to these (and similar) questions. The solution is to explicitly spell out your model. All “assumptions” can easily read off from these model specifications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distribution of residuals is of interest for linear models, not the distribution of y</title>
      <link>/2020/06/09/distribution-of-residuals-is-of-interest-for-linear-models-not-the-distribution-of-y/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/09/distribution-of-residuals-is-of-interest-for-linear-models-not-the-distribution-of-y/</guid>
      <description>Load packages library(tidyverse)  My \(y\) is not distributed according to my wishes! Let \(Y\) be a variable that we would like to model, for instance, Covid-19 cases.
Now, there’s a widely hold belief that my \(Y\) must be distributed normally, or, in some cases, following some other assumed distribution (maybe some long-tailed distribution).
However, this belief is not (strictly) true. What a linear model assumes is that the residuals are distributed normally, not the \(Y\) distribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides of my talk at ECDA 2019: Modeling of AfD election success</title>
      <link>/2019/03/16/slides-of-my-talk-at-ecda-2019-modeling-of-afd-election-success/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/03/16/slides-of-my-talk-at-ecda-2019-modeling-of-afd-election-success/</guid>
      <description>Slides of my talk at ECDA 2019 can be found here: http://data-se.netlify.com/slides/afd_ecda2019/afd-modeling-ECDA-2019.html#1.
Note that you need to be online to render the slides.
The (standalone) PDF version can be found here: http://data-se.netlify.com/slides/afd_ecda2019/afd-modeling-ECDA-2019.pdf</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poster: A Bayes model of AfD party success</title>
      <link>/2019/01/24/poster-a-bayes-model-of-afd-party-success/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/24/poster-a-bayes-model-of-afd-party-success/</guid>
      <description>At the Dozentenmeeting 2019 of the FOM Hochschule, I presented a poster of an analysis of the AfD election success, based on a Bayes multi level regression.
The poster can be downloaded here.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
