<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>psychometrics on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/psychometrics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in psychometrics on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/psychometrics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Online reaction time experiments using lab.js</title>
      <link>/2019/01/29/online-reaction-time-experiments-using-lab-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/29/online-reaction-time-experiments-using-lab-js/</guid>
      <description>Collecting data over the internet used to be fancy, some twenty years or so ago. Nowadays it can be considered standard, if not old school (collecting data using mobile apps is where the cool kids go at the moment). However, there’s one noteable exception: Collecting reaction time data over the internet remained a challenge. The reason is simply a technological artefact in that an html response time may vary, vary too much as to invalidate the signal from some behavorial reaction time research study.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparation of extraversion survey data</title>
      <link>/2017/06/24/extra_prep/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/24/extra_prep/</guid>
      <description>For teaching purposes and out of curiosity towards some psychometric questions, I have run a survey on extraversion here. The dataset has been published at OSF (DOI 10.17605/OSF.IO/4KGZH). The survey is base on a google form, which in turn saves the data in Google spreadsheet. Before the data can be analyzed, some preparation and makeup is in place. This posts shows some general makeup, typical for survey data.
Download the data and load packages Download the data from source (Google spreadsheets); the package gsheet provides an easy interface for that purpose.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>