<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>visualization on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/visualization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in visualization on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/visualization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Fallstudie zur Datenvisualisierung -- Datensatz &#34;flights&#34;</title>
      <link>/2020/11/12/fallstudie-zur-datenvisualisierung-datensatz-flights/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/12/fallstudie-zur-datenvisualisierung-datensatz-flights/</guid>
      <description>Vorbereitung Wie immer – zuerst Pakete und Daten laden:
library(tidyverse) library(nycflights13) data(&amp;quot;flights&amp;quot;)  Aufgaben zur Datenvisualisierung Die folgenden Aufgaben beziehen sich auf den Datensatz flights aus dem R-Paket nycflights13.
Visualisieren Sie die Verteilung der Verspätungen der Flüge.
 Visualisieren Sie die Verteilung der Verspätung der Flüge pro Abflugsort.
 Visualisieren Sie den Zusammenhang von Verspätung und Tageszeit. Reduzieren Sie dabei Overplotting. Tipp: Anstelle von geom_point() mal geom_bin2d() ausprobieren.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing decision trees</title>
      <link>/2020/10/17/visualizing-decision-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/17/visualizing-decision-trees/</guid>
      <description>Load packages library(tidyverse) #remotes::install_github(&amp;quot;grantmcdermott/parttree&amp;quot;) library(parttree) library(rpart) library(rpart.plot) library(parsnip) library(titanic) library(tidyverse)  Train learner Build the tree using parsnip with rpart as the model engine:
set.seed(123) titanic_train$Survived = as.factor(titanic_train$Survived) ti_tree = decision_tree() %&amp;gt;% set_engine(&amp;quot;rpart&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;% set_mode(&amp;quot;classification&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;% fit(Survived ~ Pclass + Age, data = titanic_train)  Plot the model partitions titanic_train %&amp;gt;% ggplot(aes(x=Pclass, y=Age)) + geom_jitter(aes(col=Survived), alpha=0.7) + geom_parttree(data = ti_tree, aes(fill=Survived), alpha = 0.1) + theme_minimal() Plot the tree</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ornaments with ggformula</title>
      <link>/2019/02/12/ornaments-with-gformula/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/12/ornaments-with-gformula/</guid>
      <description>Since some time, there’s a wrapper for ggplot2 available, bundled in the package ggformula. One nice thing is that in that it plays nicely with the popular R package mosaic. mosaic provides some useful functions for modeling along with a tamed and consistent syntax. In this post, we will discuss some “ornaments”, that is, some details of beautification of a plot. I confess that every one will deem it central, but in some cases in comes in handy to know how to “refine” a plot using ggformula.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing mean values between two groups  - the tidyverse way</title>
      <link>/2018/06/10/visualizing-summary-statistics-the-tidyverse-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/10/visualizing-summary-statistics-the-tidyverse-way/</guid>
      <description>A frequent job in data visualizing is to present summary statistics. In this post, I show one way to plot mean values between groups using the tidyverse approach in comparison to the mosaic way.
library(tidyverse) data(mtcars) library(mosaic) library(knitr) library(sjmisc) library(sjPlot) Visualizing mean values between two groups First, let’s compute the mean hp for automatic cars (am == 0) vs. manual cars (am == 1).
mtcars %&amp;gt;% group_by(am) %&amp;gt;% summarise(hp_am = mean(hp)) -&amp;gt; hp_am Now just hand over this data frame of summarized data to ggplot:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing around with geo mapping: combining demographic data with spatial data</title>
      <link>/2018/05/28/playing-around-with-geo-mapping-combining-demographic-data-with-spatial-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/28/playing-around-with-geo-mapping-combining-demographic-data-with-spatial-data/</guid>
      <description>In this post, we will play around with some basic geo mapping. More preciseyl, we will explore some easy ways to plot a choropleth map.
First, let’s load some geo data from Bundeswahlleiter, and combine it with some socio demographic data from the same source.
Preparation Let’s load some packages:
library(tidyverse) ## Warning: package &amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39; was built under R version 3.5.1 library(sf) library(viridis) suppressPackageStartupMessages(library(googleVis)) Geo data:
my_path_wahlkreise &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;~/Documents/datasets/geo_maps/btw17_geometrie_wahlkreise_shp/Geometrie_Wahlkreise_19DBT.shp&amp;quot; file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Error bars for interaction effects with nominal variables</title>
      <link>/2017/04/18/moderator-errorbars/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/18/moderator-errorbars/</guid>
      <description>Moderator effects (ie., interaction or synergy effects) are a topic of frequent interest in many sciences braches. A lot ink has been spilled over this topic (so did I, eg., here).
However, in that post I did now show how to visualize error in case of nominal (categorical) independent variable, and categorical moderator.
Luckily, visualization of this case is quite straight forward with ggplot2.
First, some data and packages to be loaded:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
