<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rmarkdown on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/rmarkdown/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rmarkdown on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/rmarkdown/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Force bibtex to show the exact date</title>
      <link>/2018/12/29/force-bibtex-to-show-the-exact-date/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/29/force-bibtex-to-show-the-exact-date/</guid>
      <description>Citing (aka scientific citation) is quite straight forward in RMarkdown. However, there are some shortcomings. Primarily, as citations are rendered via Pandoc’s reference engine, bibtex is used as a standard. Though is quite commonly used, bibtex has been, over and above, replaced by biblatex. biblatex is much more straight forward than bibtex (as text is formatted using latex and not bibtex, still making use of bibtex for the collection of references).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using BibLaTeX instead of Bibtex in Rmarkdown for finer control</title>
      <link>/2018/12/28/using-biblatex-instead-of-bibtex-in-rmarkdown-for-finer-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/28/using-biblatex-instead-of-bibtex-in-rmarkdown-for-finer-control/</guid>
      <description>As a standard, bibtex is used as a citation-renderer in Pandoc’s Markdown, that is, in RMarkdown as well. bibtex is useful for a fair amount of citation task, but biblatex allows for a finer control. For instance, multiple bibliographies for one document are possible.
For instance, citing a newspaper article using bibtex left me scratching my head, as I wanted to have the exact day of the date (not only the year) cited.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generating mass reports using Rmarkdown in R</title>
      <link>/2018/12/19/generating-mass-reports/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/19/generating-mass-reports/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes, one document must be recreated in similar fashions a lot of times. For instance, invoices to customers, grading schemes for students, progress reports in projects, and so on. In this post, I demonstrate one way to do that in R using RMarkdown.
Specifically, it is assumed that there’s a tabular data set, where each row refers to a document instance (eg., a mail or report to one given person), and each column holds the variables to appear in each reports (see examples below).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Image paths in Hugo/blogdown</title>
      <link>/2018/11/28/image-paths-in-hugo-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/11/28/image-paths-in-hugo-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>Images from R are instantly included into (R) markdown files, and the same applies for blogdown posts.
See:
x &amp;lt;- 1:10 plot(x) However, for external images - such as photos - things are more complicated. First, all is still fine, if an image is found on some URL/server on the internet:
knitr::include_graphics(&amp;quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/1/1b/R_logo.svg/310px-R_logo.svg.png&amp;quot;) Of course, one can apply direct markdown syntax for including external images:
![](https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/1/1b/R_logo.svg/310px-R_logo.svg.png){width=20%} Now assume we are in an R project that gives the base for a blogdown blog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible academic writing with RMarkdown - Talk at DGPs 2018</title>
      <link>/2018/09/03/reproducible-academic-writing-with-rmarkdown-talk-at-dgps-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/03/reproducible-academic-writing-with-rmarkdown-talk-at-dgps-2018/</guid>
      <description>Talk at DGPs 2018.
Get slides here: http://data-se.netlify.com/slides/rmd-writing/rmd-writing_dgps2018.html.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk - Predictors of AfD party success in the 2017 elections. A Bayesian modeling  approach</title>
      <link>/2018/09/02/predictors-of-afd-party-success-in-the-2017-elections-a-bayesian-modeling-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/02/predictors-of-afd-party-success-in-the-2017-elections-a-bayesian-modeling-approach/</guid>
      <description>Talk at DGPs 2018.
Get slides here http://data-se.netlify.com/slides/afd_dgps2018/afd_dgps2018.html</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to cite &#34;in press&#34; using Bibtex</title>
      <link>/2018/07/01/how-to-cite-in-press-using-bibtex/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/07/01/how-to-cite-in-press-using-bibtex/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to cite in markdown, a short primer</title>
      <link>/2018/03/26/how-to-cite-in-markdown-a-short-primer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/26/how-to-cite-in-markdown-a-short-primer/</guid>
      <description>I would never write a paper again using Word - except I would be forced, too, what will happen, I think. But similarly, I don’t want to write papers using Latex - too many curly braces.
Best of both worlds: Markdown. Comes with “builtin” R.
Here’s an example how to do scholarly citation in markdown.
In-Text citation Use this notation, to cite some book or paper or whatever:
The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly face similarly difficulties [@thedude2012].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yart - Yet Another Markdown Report Template</title>
      <link>/2017/11/15/yart/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/15/yart/</guid>
      <description>It would be useful to have a RMarkdown template for typical (academic) reports such as class assigments and bachelor/master thesises. The LaTeX class &amp;ldquo;report&amp;rdquo; provides a suitable format for that. This package provides a simple wrapper around this class built on the standard pandoc template.
Thanks to Yart, ie, this package leans on earlier work by Aaron Wolen in his pandoc-letter repository, and extends it for use from R via the rmarkdown package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two r plots side by sind in a Rmd-File - UPDATE</title>
      <link>/2017/10/12/two-r-plots-side-by-sind-in-a-rmd-file/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/12/two-r-plots-side-by-sind-in-a-rmd-file/</guid>
      <description>UPDATE 2018-12-03
Thanks to a comment by Katharina Hees and Joyce, I know know how to plot two images side by side in an Rmd file.
I kept wondering who to plot two R plots side by side (ie., in one “row”) in a .Rmd chunk. Here’s a way, well actually a number of ways, some good, some … not.
library(tidyverse) library(gridExtra) library(grid) library(png) library(downloader) library(grDevices) data(mtcars) Plots from ggplot Say, you have two plots from ggplot2, and you would like them to put them next to each other, side by side (not underneath each other):</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>