<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Programming on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Programming on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming with dplyr: Part 03, working with strings</title>
      <link>/2017/08/09/dplyr_strings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/09/dplyr_strings/</guid>
      <description>More on programming with dplyr: converting quosures to strings In this post, we have programmed a simple function using dplyr&amp;rsquo;s programming capabilities based on tidyeval; for more intro to programming with dplyr, see here.
In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll go one step further and programm a function where a quosure will be turned to a string. Why this? Because quite a number of functions out there except strings as input parameters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming with dplyr: Part 02, writing a function</title>
      <link>/2017/07/06/prop_fav/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/06/prop_fav/</guid>
      <description>Recently, since dplyr &amp;lt;= 0.6.0 a new way of dealing with NSE was introduced, called tidyeval. As with every topic that begs our attention, the question &amp;ldquo;why bother&amp;rdquo; is in place. Theone answer is &amp;ldquo;you&amp;rsquo;ll need this stuff if you want to lock dplyr verbs inside a function&amp;rdquo;. Once you like dplyr and friends, a natural second step is to use the ideas not only for interactive use, but for more &amp;ldquo;programming&amp;rdquo; type, ie.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A second look to grouping with dplyr</title>
      <link>/2017/06/28/second_look_group_by/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/28/second_look_group_by/</guid>
      <description>The one basic idea of dplyr is that each function should focus on one job. That&amp;rsquo;s why there are no functions such as compute_sumamries_by_group_with_robust_variants(df). Rather, summarising and grouping are seen as different jobs which should be accomplished by different functions. And, in turn, that&amp;rsquo;s why group_by, the grouping function of dplyr, is of considerable importance: this function should do the grouping for each operation whatsoever.
Let&amp;rsquo;s load all tidyverse libraries in one go:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming with dplyr: Part 01, introduction</title>
      <link>/2017/06/28/prog_dplyr_01/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/28/prog_dplyr_01/</guid>
      <description>Like for [others], Hadley Wickham&amp;rsquo;s dplyr, and more generally, the tidyverse approach has considerably changed the I do data analyses. Most notably, the pipe (coming from magrittr by Stefan Milton Bache, see here) has creeped into nearly every analyses I, do.
That is, is every analyses except for functions, and other non-interactive stuff. In those programming contexts, the dplyr way does not work, due to its non standard evaluation or NSE for short.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>