<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Markdown on Data Se</title>
    <link>/tags/markdown/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Markdown on Data Se</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/markdown/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World, this is Blogdown</title>
      <link>/2017/11/21/hello-world-this-is-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/21/hello-world-this-is-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>My blog at https://sebastiansauer.github.io/posts/ has moved. It is now here! This is the new home of my blog. In (the unlikely) case you are asking yourself “Why did you move your blog?”, here is the answer.
I was using Jekyll at Github pages which is great as long as you do not have a lot of R in your posts. But I did have a lot of R in my posts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Different ways to set figure size in RMarkdown</title>
      <link>/2016/11/02/figure_sizing_knitr/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/02/figure_sizing_knitr/</guid>
      <description>Markdown is thought as a &amp;ldquo;lightweight&amp;rdquo; markup language, hence the name markdown. That&amp;rsquo;s why formatting options are scarce. However, there are some extensions, for instance brought by RMarkdown.
One point of particular interest is the sizing of figures. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at some ways how to size a figure with RMarkdown.
We take some data first:
data(mtcars) names(mtcars)  ## [1] &amp;quot;mpg&amp;quot; &amp;quot;cyl&amp;quot; &amp;quot;disp&amp;quot; &amp;quot;hp&amp;quot; &amp;quot;drat&amp;quot; &amp;quot;wt&amp;quot; &amp;quot;qsec&amp;quot; &amp;quot;vs&amp;quot; &amp;quot;am&amp;quot; &amp;quot;gear&amp;quot; ## [11] &amp;quot;carb&amp;quot;  Not let&amp;rsquo;s plot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple (R-)Markdown template for &#39;Onepager-reports&#39; etc. </title>
      <link>/2016/10/05/template-onepager/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/10/05/template-onepager/</guid>
      <description>In my role as a teacher, I (have to) write a lot of marking feedback reports. My university provides a website to facilitate the process, that&amp;rsquo;s great. I have also been writing my reports with Pages, Word, or friends. But somewhat cooler, more attractive, and more reproducible would be using (a markup language such as) Markdown. Basically, that&amp;rsquo;s easy, but it would be of help to have a template that makes up a nice and nicely formatted report, like this:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to add a logo to a slidify presentation</title>
      <link>/2016/07/05/slidify-logo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/07/05/slidify-logo/</guid>
      <description>reading time: 15-20 min.
Slidify is a cool tool to render HTML5 slide decks, see here, here or here for examples.
Features include:
 reproducibility. You write your slide deck as you would write any other text, similar to Latex/Beamer. But you write using Markdown, which is easier and less clumsy. As you write plain text, you are free to use git. modern look. Just a website, nothing more. But with cool, modern features.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>